Guide to the Jay and Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers TAM.083
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Jay Leyda Papers
  - Subseries E: Other Projects
    - Dickinson, Emily: published material by Jay Leyda, 1955-1957 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Dickinson, Emily: reference material, drafts, correspondence, 1952-1987 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Dickinson, Emily: reviews, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - "Dictionary of Politics and Film" (Projects); c. 1972, ca.1972 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - "Direction": Jay Leyda advisory editor for film (5 issues), 1939-1942 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Exhibition "Art of the American Negro", 1940 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Exhibition "Before Hollywood" (curated by Leyda), 1983-1986 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Film, African (notes, newspaper clippings), undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Film, Czech (notes, review), undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - "Film begets Film" (newspaper clippings), 1964-1967 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - "Film begets Film" (notes, German edition), 1967 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Film Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - "Film Center Gazette", 1978-1979 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Film, general reference material 1; 1960s - 70s, 1960s -19 70s (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Film, general reference material 2; 1960s-70s, 1960s-1970s (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Film, German (leaflets, programs), 1955-1982 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Film, Japanese (notes, articles, lists), 1969-1973 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - "Film Music Series": tentative programs, undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Films - leaflets, programs etc.; 1970s (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - "Film Quarterly" (notes, drafts, correspondence), undated (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - "Film Quarterly" (notes, drafts, correspondence), 1933-1945 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Film script "Animation - An Art for the Future?" (John Hubley), 1974 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Film script "Automatic Gain Control", undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Film script "Conquistador" (Jay Leyda & Anne Green), 1943 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Film script "Erzahlungen aus der Neuen Welt" (DEFA), 1968 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Film script: Film on Russian-American Friendship (Jay Leyda), undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Film script: Melville Film, 1978-1979 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Film script "Rhoda", undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Film script "The Green Island", undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Film script "World Unity" (Jay Leyda); 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Films found and to be found, mostly Dutch (notes), undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Germany: State Film Archives, GDR (correspondence, work agreement), 1964-1965 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Griffith, D.W., 1936-1975 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation - fellowship application, 1931-1942 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Guild Theatre (program themes), undated (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - "Heroes" A Farce by Jay Leyda & Leo T. Hurwitz, 1951 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Hollywood lectures on film, 1945-1946 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - International Film Seminars Minutes; 11-May-79, 1979 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Kafka, Franz (Clippings, photos, notes), undated (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Lecture & class notes, 1969-1981 (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Maddow, Ben "A Sunday Between Wars" (typescript), 1984 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Maddow, Ben "Psalm of Twelve Fridays" (typescript), undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Maddow, Ben (seasonal greetings/writings), undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Maddow, Ben "The Glass Poet" (typescript), undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Melville articles by Jay Leyda, 1948-1985 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Melville correspondence, 1967-1986 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - "Melville Log" dust cover, book reviews, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Melville (reference material), 1949-1985 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Metcalf, Paul: series of readings, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Meyer, Carl "A Tribute to Carl Meyer (1894-1944)" pamphlet, 1947 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Meyers, Sidney "Vision is my Dwelling Place" by Jay Leyda, 1969 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Mills, Constance Quinby "A String of Pearls" (poems), 1963 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous ("Germinations") project proposals, notes 1, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous ("Germinations") project proposals, notes 2, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous typescripts by various authors; 1970s - 80s, ca.1970-1989 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes by Jay Leyda, undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous writings by Jay Leyda, undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous writings by Jay Leyda, 1930-1979 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Mussorgsky (correspondence, articles by Jay Leyda); 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - National Board of Review of Motion Pictures; c. 1933, ca.1933 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - New School: course on film making, 1938-1939 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - New York University: courses, flyers, newspaper clippings, 1974-1982 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Photography: Leyda as photographer, 1932-1935 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Project proposal for study in Japan, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Proposal to Col. Frank Capra; 1942?, ca.1942 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Rachmaninoff: "Sergey Rachmaninoff: A Lifetime in Music" book reviews, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Realist Film News (Australian newsletter), 1956 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Script Magazine: Clippings on Stage and Screen by A. Jopfin (Leyda aka?), 1947 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Swigmore, Douglas: "Selections from the Lone Pine Book of Modern Verse"; c. 1973, ca.1973 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Strohheim, Erich von; c. 1973, ca.1973 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Teaching Materials -- Reading Lists and Syllabi, 1981-1982 (Box Shared Tamiment 193, Folder 10)
    - "Voices of Film Experience" proposal, reviews, 1974-1977 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - "Voices of Film Experience" book proposal, contract; c. 1973-78, ca.1973-1978 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Weinberg, Herman G. "The Man with the Movie Camera", 1966 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Yale University (faculty list), 1970 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - York University courses on film of Asia & Africa, 1972 (Box 27, Folder 17)
- Series II: Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers
  The Si-Lan Chen Leyda papers document her dancing career and personal activities. The small biographical subseries contains her FBI file, and documents related to her travels. Si-Lan Chen's correspondence is principally with her family and Jay Leyda. There is also correspondence with Pearl S. Buck and Langston Hughes, and a file relating to immigration issues. Her dance career is documented by programs, flyers, dance notations and drawings, a scrapbook, and radio interview transcripts. Her writings include the typescript of her autobiography, Footnote to History (1984), a diary, autobiographical notebooks, and unpublished writings.
  - Subseries A: Biographical
    - FBI-file and correspondence, 1944-1979 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - FBI-file, 1952-1971 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Passports - British, Chinese, 1932-1943 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Soviet Union documents, 1931-1935 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - United States documents, 1942 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence
    - Correspondence (envelopes); 1930s-40s, ca.1930-1949 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence (general), 1929-1986 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Buck, Pearl S., 1942 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Chen, Carmen, 1945 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Chen, Eugene, 1929-1944 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Chen family misc., 1931-1938 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Chen, Jack, 1931-1985 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Chen, Jay, 1982-1984 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Chen, Yolanda, 1929-1941 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Chen, Yolanda, 1942-1946 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Chen, Yolanda, 1947-1983 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Chen, Yuan Tsung, 1971-1987 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Ewen, Kay (Kathleen); 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1933-1946 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Immigration issues, 1926-1978 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Leyda, Jay, undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1933-1935 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1936-1940 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1941-1944 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1946-1973 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Pilgrim, Philip, 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Rene, Natalie, 1929-1950 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Subseries C: Dance and Other Activities
    - Chinese dance and drama, 1970 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Dance notes, notation, undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Programs, flyers, tickets; 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Programs, flyers, tickets; 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Radio interview transcripts, 1938-1948 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Reviews, press comments; 1930s-40s, 1930-1949 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Scrap book (newspaper clippings), 1932-1939 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Subseries D: Writings
    - Address and note books, undated (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Articles by Si Lan Chen, 1941-1982 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Chen, Jack: Articles and writings, 1938-1950 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Chen, Jack: Drawings, 1933-1936 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Diary, 1942 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - "Footnote to history" (correspondence), 1942 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 1, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 2, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 3, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 4, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Printed Sheet Music and Handwritten Scores, undated (Box 32, Box 36)
    - "The road to Peking: an idea for a Hope-Crosby-Lamour film" (typescript); 1943 [?], ca.1943 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - "The summer of my life" (autobiographical notebook) Vol. 1, 1936 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - "The summer of my life" (autobiographical notebook) Vol. 2, 1936 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - "The summer of my life" (autobiographical notebook) Vol. 3, 1941 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Unpublished writings, undated (Box 31, Folder 11)
- Series III: Photographs and Graphics
  The photographs and graphic materials series provides documentation of several stages in the lives of Jay Leyda and Si-Lan Chen. It is particularly strong in childhood and family snapshots of each including a small photograph album from each family. There are portraits and snapshots of the pair in the 1930s when they first met. Other highlights in the collection are a series of photoprints by Jack Chen, Si-Lan's brother, taken in China, probably during the mid-40's; an article with photographs in the War Worker (May 1944, Los Angeles) about Si-Lan Chen's dancing; photoprints of the 1964 "Bartelby" production at Oberlin (Leyda wrote the libretto for Aschaffenburg's opera); studio performance and movie production shots of Si-Lan; a snapshot of Luis Bunuel and his sister, Conchita in 1969 at a cottage near Madrid; and a group of graphics and photoprints collected for "Dianyang."
  - Art Photographs (Photographed by Jay Leyda), 1929-circa 1930 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Art Photographs (Taken by Jay Leyda), 1929-1930 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - "Bartelby" Production Photographs, 1964 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Ben Maddow Photographs and Poem "A Wedding Hymn", undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Copies of Art Works, undated (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - "Dianying", circa 1968-1972 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Dickinson Family Silhouettes, 1955, undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - "Footnote to History" Photographs, Negatives, and Graphics, circa 1930s-1960s, undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Jack Chen Photographs, undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Jane Reece Portraits of Jay Leyda, circa 1928 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Jay Leyda Portraits and School Pictures, undated, 1934, 1960 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Jay Leyda at Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers Award Luncheon, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Kafka's Grave and Luis Bunuel, 1969 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - "Liberation News Service" Cover, December 4, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Med Hondo (Meg Xohgo?) Negatives and Transparencies, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Moscow Art Theatre Negatives, undated (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - New York Scenes, 1850s-1860s (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - Personal: Family and Friends, 1920s-1940s, 1960s, undated (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - "Photos 1928-1947" (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - Photo Album, undated (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - Photo Album, undated (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - Photo Album, Moscow (includes note by Jack Chen), May 1928 (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - Pin and Ribbon, 1960 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - "Russian Painting 1700-1917" by Jack Chen, 1948 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Si-Lan Chen Miscellaneous, undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Si-Lan Chen Movie Production Stills, circa 1946 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Si-Lan Chen Portraits, undated (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Si-Lan Chen Studio Performance Shots, undated (Box 34, Folder 5-7)
  - Stamps, undated (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - "Stills for Russian Film?", circa 1920s (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified Woman, undated (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Watercolors and Drawings: Loose Items, undated (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Watercolors and Drawings: Notebooks, undated (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - "The War Worker" (Featuring Article on Si-Lan Chen), 1944 (Box Shared Tamiment OS001)
  - Si-Lan Chen: Portrait, Posters (in Spanish), and Group Photograph, undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS001)
  - Films: "Printed Sheet Music and Hand-printed Scores", 1974-08; cuid43078 (Reel 1, Reel 2)